<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Writing by Andrew</title><description/><link>https://writingbyandrew.com/</link><language>en</language><copyright>Copyright 2021, Ronalds Vilcins</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><generator>Hugo - gohugo.io</generator><docs>http://cyber.harvard.edu/rss/rss.html</docs><atom:link href="https://ronaldsvilcins.com/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><item><title>The Murder of Lydia Stewart</title><link>https://writingbyandrew.com/2021/02/27/the-murder-of-lydia-stewart/</link><description>&lt;p>The kids at school think that Lydia Stewart moved away, but I know better. Lydia died fourteen days ago on Friday, May the Twelfth. This would be an odd thing for me to know, save for two essential truths:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>I watched the hearse carry her body away&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I killed Lydia Stewart&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>So now I spend my daily hour in AP Literature staring at the back of the foreign exchange student who moved up to take her seat in the first row. Wondering what she would be thinking about right now. Trying to figure out if she was the sort of person who actually did the reading or just copied the online summary like the rest of us. Sitting here waiting for her to die the second time, when the only memories of her that remain are yearbook signatures and club photos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Before we continue you should know that I did not know Lydia Stewart. Well, not know-know, if that makes sense. That category of people that belongs to the once-conversations at the coffee shop and pleasantries at the airport. Another one for the crowd in the back of my mind. We probably would never have spoken at all had we not been lumped together for a biology project a year before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Maybe that would’ve been better.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lydia was intelligent. And not the “wow you’re smart” sort of smart. People smart. Eyes that bore beneath your skin and see who you are. Yes, these were things I just assumed (because she didn’t talk much anyways) but you can always sort of tell with that sort.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>She went to class, turned in work on time, and that is the end of the story I know. I spent the first week looking back trying to find pictures of the two of us together. Trying to form a narrative that neatly begins and ends with us. Hours of scouring old scrapbooks and yearbooks turned up only a sole fifth grade class photo. No Shakespeare, no poetic ending or twist, just regular fucked-up life.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Did she know then that I would be the one who ended it all? That I would choose the spot on the page that the words stopped? Looking up out of the photo, would she recognize the murder weapon tucked in my pocket?&lt;/p></description><author>ronalds.vilcins@gmail.com (Ronalds Vilcins)</author><guid>https://writingbyandrew.com/2021/02/27/the-murder-of-lydia-stewart/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Strawberry Ice Cream</title><link>https://writingbyandrew.com/2020/08/07/strawberry-ice-cream/</link><description>&lt;p>Everett checked his phone. &lt;em>10:23 pm.&lt;/em> In three minutes and seventeen seconds, Everett will be struck by a drunk driver in a purple sedan while crossing the intersection at Edison Rd. and Bellatrix Ave., receiving severe body-wide blunt force trauma, then lifted up and over the hood of the car to rest face-down on the road. Everett will die five feet and ten inches tall, despite having lived at six feet, on account of having several vertebrae of his lower spine shattered. In his wake will be a trail of pinkish-red sludge measuring seventeen yards from the site of initial contact. The declared cause of death will be “internal hemorrhaging following rupture of the right pulmonary artery due to major chest trauma,” though a critic may point to the crumpled plastic bin next to his body. The driver in question, former security guard Philip Walker, will lead a successful life of recovery and penance following his stint in prison, becoming a best-selling author.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But that is neither here nor there. The time was 10:23 and Everett was walking back from a local grocery store. He smiled to himself, some earnestness to his step and a quart of ice cream in hand. The cargo had set him back nine dollars, but he didn’t mind—the evening was going well. He had surprised his girlfriend, Amber, with homemade dinner. And sure, he had forgotten to pick up some ice cream beforehand, but things like that are hard to remember when cooking. Amber had tried to come with him, but he insisted that she rest. This was his pilgrimage to take alone.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He breathed with a small opening to his mouth, letting air flow in. He felt the cool air mixing with his mint gum, freezing the caps of his molars. He turned it over and over with his tongue, imagining that he was lowering his body temperature to keep the ice cream from melting. Amber had named the sensation once. Cold spice? Something like that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The air was rich with pine. Trees not too dissimilar from those by his childhood home. Large, green, welcoming. Those very picturesque sorts of things that you’d take family photos in front of. His father had helped him build a treehouse out of pine. It had turned out as more of a shed, really. “You could fall out of it if it was in a tree.” Everett brushed aside the incomplete thought with his hand, so that one observing may think he was receiving perfume.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Catching his wrist at just the right angle, moonlight glinted at his eye. He raised his arm, checking his watch. &lt;em>10:29.&lt;/em> The black arms gazed back through the cracked face. A family heirloom passed down by his paternal grandfather. The story went that it was crushed when he was shot down somewhere over Germany back in 1943. The face was stuck. No one had seen it fit for repair. Amber and him spoke about it often. She thought that it was a very handsome piece that would look good restored. Everett disagreed. It was a good luck charm.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Also glinting was a diamond-embedded silver band in his pocket, having caught a shallow ray of light from the opening. He hadn’t planned on proposing any time soon, or so he told himself. He enjoyed holding it. Feeling its weight. He would rub his hand over the center diamond the way he would with seashells when he was younger, letting it hook on the small crests of his palm. It was in need of a better carrying arrangement. Everett had lost the case only half an hour after the purchase, setting it down on a subway bench to take a closer look at the ring. It wasn’t overly extravagant, as he couldn’t afford too much, but it was nice.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He placed his hand inside the pocket to feel it now, cradling it gently, as if a father to a newborn. Letting it tumble between his fingers, he caressed it with the back of his nails. His walking slowed, trying not to make a sound.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Around twenty feet before the intersection at Edison and Bellatrix was a blind turn where several lampposts had gone out. The police department had assigned an officer to set up a reflective sign that day and watch out for speeding cars, but the task was left undone. Everett nodded at the sleeping cop as he passed.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He could use some sleep himself. The last two days he had worked a combined twenty-three hours. He figured that he should talk to his supervisor about it, but he needed the job. Name-brand ice cream was expensive. But he didn’t need to worry about that now, because it was 10:25 and twenty-three seconds on a Friday in February, and he was happy.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Happy, like the first time Everett met Amber at a stupid ice cream social back in college. Everett still wasn’t sure why he’d gone. The ice cream was terrible. It was all very much melted when he arrived. She was forward. Asked him for his name and out on a date, in that order. Amber wasn’t melted at all. She knew who she was, what she would do. Bachelors, med school, marriage, retirement.
Everett had never been sure about things. He was no great achiever or leader of men; the greatest footnote to his name was a first place finish in an essay contest to name a city street, way back in the seventh grade. He won by writing about Daniel Bellatrix, a veteran who spent his free time volunteering in a local library. Mr. Bellatrix didn’t seem extraordinary to Everett at the time, but apparently he was enough to win the twenty-five dollar prize. Everett hoped to have something named after him one day. A street seemed a bit too grand, but maybe a bench. Yes, a bench seemed wholly pleasant.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He arrived at the stop sign. The intersection at Edison and Bellatrix was not a busy one. So it was purely out of his own decision that Everett decided to stop and wait for a moment, perched on the curb before crossing. His grandmother had told him once that intersections were a nice spot to wait and think. He didn’t know about all that but they were a convenient spot to look around. A buildup of trash by the storm drain nearest to him caused a frown. Maybe Amber would join him for a trash walk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He checked the road three times before crossing (for his mother’s sake), even though there wasn’t a car to be seen, and stepped out into the crosswalk.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Everett’s second-to-last thought came at 10:26 and seven seconds: that the space on the street in-between the dim lampposts and pine trees could be outer space. It certainly seemed dark enough. He jumped from foot to foot. He was floating.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Touching down, he heard a soft clinking sound on the ground.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>The ring…Fuck should’ve used a bag…Where—&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He doubled over to search in the middle of the street, squinting through the darkness. As such, he was perfectly unaware when a purple sedan with its headlights off soared around the blind corner at ninety miles an hour.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The container of ice cream burst on impact, sending chunks spraying out into the surrounding pines and dusting the landscape with a deep pink spray. However, the small ring in his pocket was thrown down the street where it remained rather intact, skidding several yards to come to a stop next to a recently kicked penny.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It would be found a week later by a local high schooler and pawned off for two hundred and seventeen dollars.&lt;/p></description><author>ronalds.vilcins@gmail.com (Ronalds Vilcins)</author><guid>https://writingbyandrew.com/2020/08/07/strawberry-ice-cream/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 07 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Poolside</title><link>https://writingbyandrew.com/2020/07/25/poolside/</link><description>&lt;p>I was there first, as usual. The sky was still black. The parking lot was empty, save for one large grey van parked in the corner. The van was the home of an impoverished man by the name Derrick-or-something-like-that who lived with two undersized German shepherds. I always thought it was a bit odd that he would pick the one broken lamppost to park under. You would think that the constant flickering would keep you up but maybe he knows something I don’t.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I parked in the opposite corner from the van, like Mom told me to. It always felt a bit inhuman but apparently this-is-not-a-hill-to-die-on-and-Jesus-died-for-my-sins so I just did like she said. My father would grimace with his eyes but say statistics-are-statistics and that would be that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Well fuck. The dumpster is overflowing again. We (as in the evergrateful-team-family that is the pool staff) were currently in a feud with our local garbage truck drivers. Apparently John or someone had propped up a piece of serrated glass of “substantial size” on the side of the dumpster. When the driver went to load it in, he gave himself a cut that resulted in an ER visit and a weekend health and safety seminar. It seemed kinda stupid to me. Why didn’t the driver just load the dumpster and leave the glass? I heard whoever it was got a nice settlement though, so that’s how it goes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Whatever reason aside, now someone would have to load up their car with whichever garbage bags hadn’t split open and drive them over to the gym three blocks away which had more than enough room. The gym owner didn’t like it very much but someone’s ex worked over there so the gate to the dumpsters was usually unlocked.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I walked over the pool gate and tested it. The interior bar rattled against its enclosure on the other side. John didn’t trust any of us with the keys, which I guess makes sense, but then again maybe he should show up first.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Crawling through the side window the busted lock always felt a little strange. When doing something that looks as crime-y as breaking into your own workplace, you feel an urge to look over your shoulder to make sure that no one is watching to think it’s a crime. But I think that makes it look more like a crime, like you know it’s wrong. Coming through to the other side, I turned on my phone flashlight to see what I was stepping on. There was a small table to step onto but oftentimes someone would leave their towel or sunglasses.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I’m in. The soft blink of the microwave clock’s 12:00 oriented me while also reminding me that it was my turn to clean it. There would be time for that later.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Squinting my eyes in anticipation, I flicked my palm upwards at the lightly colored square on the wall to turn on the office lights. The sharp buzz of the overhead lights abruptly cut through the silence of the room, filling my ears then dissipating like water.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I gave my finger to the clock-in machine and that was that. I was again part of the machine. Walking out of the staffroom to the deck always spooked me a bit. Thousands of gallons of water pressed flat at the surface sheening at me. I walked quickly into the equipment closet.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The door creaked open on hinges last surveyed by some guy back in the 60s, revealing a small concrete interior. The walls stood barricaded behind rows of metal shelving, each flush with disinfectant and paper towels. The floor was lined with boxes of whole-purchased trash bags, all sorted to be picked up then thrown down again.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You’d think the room with all the cleaning supplies would be cleanest, and I guess it looked that way. The floor in the center of the room had a nice shine to it and the thick huff of chemicals left a bit of a sunshine haze. But behind the shelves dirt filled out every crack and crease of the room as if it was foam coming to rest on the shore. Half-buried insect corpses looked on with blank eyes at a sun unseen behind the metal door.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Clamping some disinfectant between my elbows, I grabbed a bottle of bleach and a roll of paper towels. I backed out of the room.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The thing about working the early morning shift is that you’re left with the most maintenance work of the entire day. Whatever filth had collected or objects that had been broken the previous afternoon and evening were left for me. I think John knew that it fell on me, but he didn’t seem to mind much. These days I’m not sure what John wants at all. He bitches about his stupid-fucking-girlfriend a lot, but the longing looks he gives at the community college water polo team says something different. Poor John.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To be frank, it wasn’t that bad. There’s a certain odd satisfaction to cleaning every inch of a bathroom. Every sweep of the floor and spray of bleach felt as if I was spreading myself. A small ownership. Possession.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Forgotten goggles, faded striped towels, reading glasses. Imagining the person behind the objects gave a greater adventure than film or books ever did. The objects rarely disappoint. They don’t leave you clamoring for a second act or commentary. They are, and the story is.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Chrrt. I’ve stepped on something. A small grey-no-green piece of paper. Fifty dollars. Some sort of blue stuff smeared over Grant’s left eye.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Suddenly that hungry feeling that consumes teenage millionaires and lottery winners was me. This could mean mint chip ice cream for the next couple months and not that discount store-brand shit that tastes like freezer-burned pizza. Or some new spoons. I did need some spoons. I suspect my last roommate stole mine on the way out. The possibilities.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A find of this value has to be protected. John wouldn’t approve. He would take it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My car. Glovebox. Under the gum.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I strode quickly back to the staffroom and jumped back through the window, stumbling down onto the concrete. Smooth.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A silver sedan was straddled next to my blue one. Not worrying. John often slept before work. Working as a night janitor was tiring.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Morning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I was in the car. The glove box opened with a soft reluctant click, where a half-pack of minty gum lay. Stashing the bill, my body slumped. I checked on John.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Asleep, caressing the steering wheel. It was a little impressive that he managed to sleep there without beeping the horn. Maybe I would be okay.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The blinking light in my side mirror said otherwise. A lone figure was outside by Derrick’s van. He was cradling his head. Was he looking over? He could feel my greed through the millimeters of steel encasing me. He was me. He was John. I was him. I am him.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I turned on the radio.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>-ome back to 87.3 The Vine playing your latest tra-&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I could see the sun now. If I left my car here it would heat up and be unpleasant to sit in after work. I would move it, just for convenience’s sake.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Backing out, I saw the figure’s head raise up in a question mark as I circled the parking lot. I made my way around to the side shaded by the trees. The bill buried in my glovebox began rattling violently. With each push of the gas closer to the van it made another attempt to lunge out, beating at the sides of a 90s faux-leather interior. I stopped.
Derrick gave a little wave through my shotgun window, five feet away. Mom’s screaming again and the radio can’t quite blanket the sound. I turned off the car and cracked the door.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Already halfway out of the car I whispered&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Mornin—&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Derrick is holding a finger against a slight grin, his other hand gesturing to the van.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>His dogs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I gave a small wave and headed back to jump through the window. Walking, I glanced back and saw him still in the same position, head slightly tilted. Curious?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It was beyond me. Opening was in fifteen, and John prefers to have both bathrooms cleaned out and chems checked before he arrives. More time to nap. He needs his rest.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There would be time to buy spoons later.&lt;/p></description><author>ronalds.vilcins@gmail.com (Ronalds Vilcins)</author><guid>https://writingbyandrew.com/2020/07/25/poolside/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>